Okay, so בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, so today's דף daf is דף
כ"ז daf chaf zayin and we start with some משנה. mishna. Now
until now with היה קורא, Hayah Korei, the name of the פרק,
perek, we've been talking about the actual act of reciting of the
שמע Shema and the discussion until now had been like the precision
of the act or the specific criteria of the act, whether it
have to be whether you have to hear what you're saying, whether
the letters have to be precisely enunciated, and I did want to
say one final thing about that before we sort of switch gears
into what we're into the next point which is, you know, I
was saying that those demands sort of reflect more of a formal
act than of the issue
of בלכתחילה b'lichatchila that we do demand both of them, that you
hear what you're saying and that they're enunciated, but בדיעבד b'diavad clearly,
but בדיעבד b'diavad even if you didn't do either of those you're
okay because of the emphasis on the כוונה, kavana, אחר כוונת הלב
הדברים, achar kavanat halev hadvarim, and that in the end, you know,
it's an act of קבלת עול מלכות שמים, kabbalas ol malchus shamayim,
even if the reciting is not so- is not totally perfect. I
did want to take a moment to sort of recognize that there
was never question about this for example when it comes to דאוונען.
davenning. All the discussion- like דאוונען davenning you're supposed to say very
softly, and all the discussion that we have about being precise with
the letters, you know, מדקדק, medakdek, you know, separating between על לבבך
al levavecha etc, there's nothing there's none of this discussion by דאוונען.
davenning. Now part of, you know, by שמונה עשרה. Shmonai Esrei. Now
part of the reason is because, you know, this is a- this
is a prescribed text, the formal text of the תורה, Torah, and
you know, but דאוונען davenning is also a prescribed text by the
Rabbis. Nevertheless, you know, here clearly there's an act of קריאת שמע,
krias shema, reciting, which is and the formal act of reciting. So
that certainly creates those לכתחילה lichatchila requirements, but בדיעבד b'diavad even without
those, you're יוצא yotzei because as one of the- one of the
ברייתות braitas mentioned, you know, emphasized רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, על לבבך,
al levavecha, that at the end of the day, even though it's
an act of reciting, it's an act of קבלת עול מלכות שמים
kabbalas ol malchus shamayim through reciting and what you're thinking and how
you're- and therefore some of those precisions in the act בדיעבד b'diavad
will not hold you back from fulfilling the מצוה. mitzvah. So now
we move from that to the next משנה, mishna, which speaks not
about the act of saying as it were, well not about the
formal criteria of the act, but again with this question of כוונה
kavana and here looking at this difference in a way also between
כוונה kavana by שמע shema and by תפילה. tfila. So as I've
just said, by שמע shema there's more of an element of reciting,
but in the end there is כוונה kavana as well. By תפילה
tfila כוונה kavana is the central aspect. So let's look at what
this משנה mishna says. האמרי דבי...
He'amreih d'bi... could you give a couple of comments about the word
כוונה? kavana? Some of our holy texts it seems to suggest intent,
right, intent
to
fulfill the מצוה, mitzvah, right, and other parts of the text it
seems to reflect the idea of comprehension.
Right. I would say there are basically three- let's- if you- thanks
for the question. If we use תפילה tfila as a model because
there the רמב"ם Rambam and some commentators, you know, sort of lay
out, there's three categories of כוונה. kavana. One is intent to fulfill
the מצוה. mitzvah. That's not what we're talking about here in any
of my comments because that's a generic question and it's not and
it's not what's specific to the nature of שמע shema and תפילה.
tfila. The second is intent meaning knowledge- awareness of what the words
mean. You know, what the words that you're saying means. And you
know, by שמונה עשרה Shmonai Esrei we say בדיעבד b'diavad if you
had on- if you knew about the first, you know, the first
ברכה bracha even if you weren't paying attention to what you were
saying in the other ברכות brachas and that's knowing the words that
are coming out of your mouth. But the third, both by שמע
shema and תפילה, tfila, is more about sort of- I- I want
to say the word intent again but there's a better word, but
sort of intent and cognizance of what is the act that you're
doing, the import of the act. So for example by תפילה, tfila,
it's being- knowing that you're עומד לפני המקום, omeid lifnei hamakom, says
the רמב"ם. Rambam. That's the central intent, being aware that you're standing
before God. And that is more significant than knowing what the words
mean, because fundamentally תפילה tfila is to stand before God. So the
way the ר' חיים Reb Chaim explains the רמב"ם Rambam is that
that you need throughout דאוונען, davenning, which ר' אפרים Reb Efraim says
means most of us wouldn't be יוצא yotzei דאוונען, davenning, but okay.
But that he says you need throughout where to know what the
words mean, that is only like for the first ברכה. bracha. But
that he says is is constitutive of what תפילה tfila is, standing
before God. So I would say by analogy the same thing about
שמע, shema, you know, when it says that the גמרא gemara hasn't
been clear when it says like till here you need כוונה. kavana.
Does it mean to know what each word means? My sense was
more that it means כוונה kavana in the sense of awareness of
what the overall import of what you're doing, the act of קבלת
עול מלכות שמים kabbalas ol malchus shamayim that through these words I
am accepting God as king and you know and and and acknowledging
my obligation of אהבת השם ahavas hashem and so on. So you
know it would be an interesting question, right, let's say I knew
the general themes of the שמע shema and the themes that have
to each פסוק, pasuk, but I didn't know what each word meant.
That would be the question. I was more emphasizing the latter rather
than the specific question of the awareness of what every word meant.
I think that that's more the emphasis here. But yes, thank you
for the question.
Would you say the emphasis specifically applies to something like תפילה? tefillah?
But for most מצוות, mitzvos, like if you give צדקה tzedakah without
understanding the context of social welfare and so on, does that...
Right, absolutely. That's the whole point, that by all מצוות mitzvos which
are fundamentally about the act, the only question is and we that
do you need to be aware that you're fulfilling a מצוה mitzvah
and we might even rule that you don't. But that's the big
generic מצוות צריכות כוונה. mitzvos tzrichos kavanah. What's unique about תפילה tefillah
and about שמע Shema is that it's not an act of דאוונינג
davening to just say words. It's an act of דאוונינג davening to
be עומד לפני המקום. omed lifnei HaMakom. It's an act of דאוונינג
davening to communicate and know what you're saying. And by שמע Shema
as well, it's not just the physical act that the words are
coming out of your mouth, by שמע Shema it is to do
it as an act of קבלת עול מלכות שמים. kabbalas ol malchus
shamayim. So yes, by שמע Shema and שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei the
כוונה kavanah is constitutive of the act itself. It's not an additional
criterion, you know, this, that's what makes it the act of saying
שמע, Shema, the act of דאוונינג. davening.
Is this a question as to whether or not speech is an
action?
Well, in general, that's true as well. Right, exactly so.
Exactly so. To what degree is speech, you know, just expressed thought,
and therefore you need the thought in order for it to be
expressed thought? Absolutely. Okay, so excellent point. And as I said, by
שמע Shema at least you have both elements because there's this act
of reciting, by שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei it is much more about
כוונה kavanah and we'll see that now as we move to this
משנה. mishna. So let's look at the משנה. mishna. האומנין קורין בראש
האילן ובראש הנדבך. Ha'umnin korin berosh ha'ilan uverosh hanidbach.
So the workers can, the laborers can read when they're at the
head of the tree. These are people that are out there picking
the fruit from the tree, or at the head of the נדבך
nidbach which is like a layer of bricks, like at a construction
site. So we would sort of say they're up there on the
girders. Okay, so there they are, they don't have to come all
the way down from being up there, what do you call that?
Not girders, what do you call that? Scaffolding, you know, they're way
up there. Right, they have to come all the way down in
order to have right כוונה kavanah to say שמע Shema or can
they say it when they're up on top? So, say it when
you're up on top. Now, this is also interesting because it's a
tension that plays out every day and that חז"ל Chazal sort of
tip one way and sadly most people who are פרום frum tip
the other way, which is between your sort of ritual, you know,
sort of requirements and doing them a hundred percent as opposed to
your responsibilities to other people. And here the question is, so there
you are, you're at the head of the tree. Well, I'll only
be able to have real כוונה kavanah for שמע Shema if I
come down. But you're being paid for your job, you're being paid,
you know, it's not fair to your employer. Okay, so that, you
know, you're being paid by the hour. So they say, you know
what, don't have a hundred percent כוונה kavanah by שמע, Shema, you
can have sufficient כוונה kavanah to be יוצא, yotzei, say it when
you're at the top of the tree.
Yes, and the surprising thing is that there's a היתר heter for
even to take a few minutes and say the שמע Shema when
you're being paid.
Right, so that also is a question as well and we'll talk
about that a little in the גמרא. Gemara. Maybe you just want
to say שמע Shema as you're working. Okay, but some of that
might be that once they say that it's allowed, then it's implicit
in the, you know, in the hire. Okay, but yes,
but that is true that, you know, you could say well maybe
you're not allowed to do it at all. Okay, so anyway, so
you say when you're at the head of the tree. מה שאין
כן לעשות כן בתפילה. Mah she'ein ken la'asos ken bitefillah. Now, that's
not the case by דאוונינג. davening. And this is exactly it, that
the requirements of כוונה kavanah by שמע, Shema, like I said, we
said the first פסוק, pasuk, the first פרשה, parsha, but we didn't
really underscore how central כוונה kavanah is and the high criteria. That
is something which is much more by דאוונינג davening and חז"ל Chazal
really want you to have a settled frame of mind before you
are דאוונינג. davening. So there you would have to come down. חתן
פטור מקריאת שמע לילה הראשון ועד מוצאי שבת אם לא עשה מעשה.
Chasan patur mikrias Shema lailah harishon ve'ad motza'ei Shabbos im lo asah
ma'aseh. The חתן, chasan, a groom,
is exempt from קריאת שמע krias Shema the first night, the wedding
night, because he's very distracted, you know, he's anxious in term because
he's going to be having sex with his bride, until the Saturday
night if they have not yet done the deed. A little translation.
So what does that mean? Because if you learn the beginning of
כתובות, Kesuvos, you see that you get married on Wednesday. So this
is four nights, you know, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, and Saturday night. So
you give him four nights and then if they haven't done it
by then, you figure he's no longer so anxious because it's already
like, you know, either whatever, he's not feeling so urgent or he's
used to the problem, so then we don't exempt him. But until
then he's very distracted and he's exempt.
Now, מעשה ברבן גמליאל שנשא אישה וקרא לילה הראשון. Ma'aseh beRabban Gamliel
shenasa ishah vekara lailah harishon. Now there's the story, Rabban Gamliel got
married and he read the first night. אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru lo
talmidav, his students said to him: למדתנו רבנו שחתן פטור מקריאת שמע.
Limadtanu rabbeinu shechasan patur mikrias Shema. Haven't you taught us that a
groom is exempt from קריאת שמע? krias Shema? How did they know
that he wasn't saying שמע Shema the first night? I don't know,
but maybe they all דאוונד. davened. Maybe the wedding was over and
somebody gave a קלאפ klap and said מנחה mincha or מעריב maariv
or whatever, and everybody started to דאוון, daven, and then what are
you doing? Get back there. So okay,
maybe the קריאת שמע krias Shema wasn't public. It is interesting to
note how much we have in ברכות Berachos about stories and stories
about רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. Second story already about רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, right? רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel kids came back from the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. He tweeted. He tweeted. Okay, so אמר להם, Amar
lahem, he said to them: איני שומע לכם לבטל ממני מלכות שמים
אפילו שעה אחת.
Eini shome'a lachem levatel
mimeni
malchus shamayim afilu sha'ah achas. I will not listen
to you to withhold from myself the yoke of heaven even for
one moment. So again, underscoring the idea of the yoke of heaven
and how central it is. And it's an interesting double-edged sword because
it's yoke of heaven it's so much that you never want to
be exempt from it and it demands that you do it. On
the other hand, presumably because it is about accepting the yoke of
heaven, we want there to be a certain amount of focus and
intent, and that's exactly the type. But he says I'm going to
be פרום frum about this and I'm going to make sure that
not even one moment. And in general, we say by the way,
it's a general thing that comes up more by תפילה. tefilla. But
a lot of the things that the גמרא Gemara says you're exempt
from דאווענינג davening because we assume you don't have enough intent. The
ראשונים Rishonim say nowadays nobody has enough intent, so you can't use
those exemptions. Because if we use those exemptions, we would never be
יוצא yotzei any דאווענינג. davening. So we have to just accept that
we have a lower level of intent than חזל Chazal wanted us
to have. And as a result, nowadays we say you don't have
this exemption of not saying שמע Shema the wedding night. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan.
האומנין קורין בראש האילן ובראש הנדבך. Ha-umnim korin berosh ha-ilan u-berosh ha-nidbach.
So the workmen read at the top of the tree and at
the top of the construction scaffold, yeah. ומתפללין בראש הזית ובראש התאנה.
U-mispallelin berosh ha-zayis u-berosh ha-te'ena.
Now they can't דאוון daven in the tree because they will be
afraid they'll fall and they won't be able to focus. But there
are some trees like an olive tree and a fig tree which
apparently have broad branches and you can situate yourself pretty well there
and דאוון daven without being afraid that you're going to fall. I
don't know if you could actually stand up, maybe you're still דאווענינג
davening sitting, but at least you're not afraid. Dov, you know about
some of this, right? You know about olive trees. What? They're low.
Oh, they're low. But presumably if you stood, you'd still be afraid
you were going to fall. Yes. So the point is less that
they're broad branches and that they're low.
The base of olive trees are thick.
The base, and you can stand in the base?
You might be able to.
Okay. All right.
It says here you can, and then the notes they're able to
stand at the top
of the olive tree.
I know, I know. I'm just saying I'm not sure what this
is assuming. It's
assuming that you can sit and דאוון daven when
you can't stand and דאוון daven you can sit and דאוון. daven.
I'm just saying it's not clear yet. There are some that say
you can even stand here, it's just, I'm saying it's not clear
to me. Right. רשי Rashi says it, so I'm just saying it's
not clear to me that that's what's being stated. It's just stating
that you're not afraid you're going to fall, but it might not
be going so far to say you should even stand. רשי Rashi
does say you stand, yeah.
They are assuming a very high degree of education on the part
of ordinary workmen because they didn't have a סידור, siddur, right? We
said yesterday they didn't, people didn't have סידורים, siddurim, they had to
have the
whole שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh by heart. Right. It is assuming, you're
right. And we're going to keep on going and talking about
alternatives to שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh or maybe going to שול shul
if you don't know the whole, actually not really. But you're right.
It's a very good point that normally we assume that a lot
of people did not know it and needed to be actually יוצא
yotzei through the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibur. So this has to assume
that they are able to do it. And they're able. Right. Unless
they're able to coordinate in the group of workers and one person
knows it and everybody else listens. I don't know if that, but
you're right. It assumes that it's possible for them to do it
by themselves.
If they're just going to be reading קריאת שמע Krias Shema and
not שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh, then the assumption is they're saying it
without the ברכות, brachos, is that correct?
That's a good question.
That is a good question. Not clear. Meaning, if, I mean, I
assume we would treat it like we would treat it nowadays, which
is
if they're going to be able to do שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh
later בזמנו, bizmano, then they'd say without ברכות brachos and then they'd
do שמע Shema with ברכות brachos and then leading into שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esreh. If they're not able to do it later בזמנו, bizmano,
then they would presumably do שמע Shema with ברכות brachos right now.
But what about סמיכת גאולה
לתפילה?
smichas
geula le-tefilla?
Yeah, so, but you're not going to get that anyway because you're
not going to be able to do not שמע בזמנו, Shma bizmano,
שמונה עשרה
בזמנו. Shmoneh Esreh bizmano. I'll have to think about that. You're right.
It's an interesting question. What happens if, would you sacrifice שמע Shema
with the ברכות brachos in order to get סמיכת גאולה לתפילה? smichas
geula le-tefilla? You could do שמע בזמנו Shema bizmano without the ברכות,
brachos, but you won't be able to do שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh,
which would take precedence? The סמיכת גאולה smichas geula or the שמע
Shema with the ברכות? brachos? You know, it's a good question. My
intuition would be the שמע Shema with the ברכות, brachos, because it
seems very much like that was the first תקנה takana of the
שמע Shema with its ברכות brachos as the full fulfillment of שמע
Shema and then they added the idea that you have to work
to be סומך גאולה לתפילה. someich geula le-tefilla. Well, you'd say the
ברוך הוא baruch hu before and a ברכה bracha after. I don't
know, no, though what you would do. Anyway, I have to think
about that. That's a good question. I'm sure it's dealt with, I
just don't know the answer off the top of my head. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. ושאר כל האילנות יורד למטה ומתפלל. U-shear kol ha-ilanos yored le-mata
u-mispallel. Okay, so that's ראש הזית ובראש התאנה. rosh ha-zayis u-berosh ha-te'ena.
ושאר כל האילנות יורד למטה ומתפלל. shear kol ha-ilanos yored le-mata u-mispallel.
Other trees, you would have to come down and דאוון. daven. ובעל
הבית בין כך ובין כך יורד למטה ומתפלל. U-ba'al ha-bayis bein kach
u-vein kach yored le-mata u-mispallel. Now, if you are the actual, the
owner, right, the employer, then we don't give you any exemption because
you know, you can take the time off. You don't want to
take the time off, but you know, but fine, you're not doing
it at somebody else's expense just at your own expense. So you
would have to come down and דאווען. daven. לפי שאין דעתו מיושבת
עליו, Lefi she'ein da'ato meyushevet alav, because he is not able to
focus. Now רש"י Rashi says everybody's not able to focus, that's the
problem. So רש"י Rashi says, yeah, but the point is you're not
able to focus and there's no counterbalancing sort of value at stake.
So for you, even if you're בראש הזית ובראש התאנה berosh hazayit
v'berosh hateina and there's not such an issue of fear, for you
we say, you know, make the sacrifice and go down because you're
not doing it at anybody else's expense.
Okay, so that's at least how רש"י Rashi explains it. It's harder
to explain why he would have more of an issue of כוונה
kavannah than them. They both have the same issue of כוונה, kavannah,
but they're doing it at his expense, he's not doing it at
anybody's expense. Okay. רמי ליה רב מרי בר ברא דבת שמואל לרבא.
Rami lei Rav Mari bar Bra d'bat Shmuel l'Rava. So רב מרי
Rav Mari the son of the daughter of שמואל Shmuel says to
רבא. Rava. Now why is it the son of the daughter of
שמואל? Shmuel? So רש"י Rashi points out that שמואל's Shmuel daughter actually
was taken captive and was
had sex with a non-Jew
and he was born from that so he was not attributed after
his father. Actually, the man actually eventually raped her. Right.
רש"י Rashi says.
Right. And the man actually eventually... but רש"י Rashi doesn't say rape.
רש"י Rashi says בא עליה. ba aleha. Right. The גמרא's Gemara always
concerned in a case
of captivity.
I understand. Well, it was right, right. I understand that. The גמרא's
Gemara always concerned in כתובות Ketubot about a case of captivity about
whether about whether you know about people will sometimes do things in
order whatever. The גמרא's Gemara concerned, obviously nobody is doing it out
of a total free will. But you know there's an aspect of
duress about the whole thing. But you know sometimes people will act
you know in certain ways in order to alleviate their situation even
if somebody's not forcing it upon them. So there is a question
within those cases of do we always assume אונס ones or not.
Anyway, but yes, obviously there's an aspect of duress about that. Anyway,
the man finally eventually even became a convert and there are stories
about him about איסור גיורא, Issur Giyora, you might have heard about
him.
But רב מרי Rav Mari was always never attributed to his father,
you know, after his father who was this non-Jew who possibly raped
his mother, but rather to his mother, the daughter of שמואל, Shmuel,
who doesn't say here who her name is, but another גמרא Gemara
says her name was רחל. Rachel. So anyway that's רב מרי Rav
Mari the son of the daughter of שמואל. Shmuel. He said to
רבא, Rava, תנן האומנין קורין בראש האילן ובנין נדבך. Tnan ha'umnin korin
berosh ha'ilan uvinyan nidbach.
So you can read at the top of the tree שמע Shema
at least. אלמא לא בעי כוונה. Alma lo ba'ei kavannah. So you
see כוונה kavannah isn't an issue at all for שמע. Shema. רמינהי,
Reminei, I'll ask him on this, הקורא את שמע צריך שיכוין לבו.
Hakorei et Shema tzarich sheyachavein libo. We said that you need כוונה
kavannah by שמע, Shema, at least for שנאמר שמע ישראל shenemar Shema
Yisrael and להלן הוא אומר, ulhalan hu omer, hear o Israel, and
it says later הסכת ושמע ישראל, hasket ushema Yisrael, give ear, pay
attention and listen Israel. מה להלן בהסכת, Ma lehalan b'hasket, the same
way later it's like pay attention, אף כאן בהסכת, af kan b'hasket,
here too pay attention. So even by שמע Shema you can't say
it's just reading. There's an aspect of כוונה. kavannah. אישתיק, Ishtik, he
was silent. ולא אמר ליה. V'lo amar lei. מידי שמיע לך בהא?
Midi shmia lach beha?
So he said to him, had you heard an answer to this,
saying back to רב מרי? Rav Mari? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said to him, הכי אמר רב ששת. Hachi amar Rav Sheshet.
Here's what I heard that רב ששת Rav Sheshet said. How do
you deal with the fact that it seems like we're not cared
about כוונה kavannah at all by שמע? Shema? Here's what רב ששת
Rav Sheshet says. והוא שבטלין ממלאכתן וקורין. V'hu shebeteilin mimlachtan vekorin.
It says ah, you see, first we assumed it was that while
they're staying at the top of the tree, they're working through שמע.
Shema. If they're saying שמע Shema as they're working. And then the
question was where, how, you need some כוונה. kavannah. They say okay
fine, you don't get down from the tree but at least you
stop working in order to say the שמע. Shema. Okay. So surely
that responds to you. There was an assumption that you can't make
any sacrifices for the sake of שמע Shema and then they say
no, you don't get down but at least you stop working and
that will be sufficient. שמע Shema doesn't need כוונה kavannah lower than
תפילה, tefillah, but a certain amount of כוונה kavannah it does, a
modicum amount it does. והתניא, Vehatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא,
baraita, בית הלל אומרים עוסקים במלאכתן וקורין. Beit Hillel omrim oskim bimlachtan
vekorin. That
you know when בית הלל Beit Hillel says ובלכתך בדרך, uvlechtacha baderech,
even if you're working you could be saying the שמע. Shema. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא בפרק ראשון הא
בפרק שני. ha beperek rishon ha beperek sheni. The first chapter and
the second chapter. First chapter is כוונה kavannah is emphasized, second chapter
not, as we saw those debates earlier. If you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, הא בפרק ראשון, ha beperek rishon, תוספות Tosafot says לאו דוקא
נקט פרק ראשון דהיינו אליבא דרבא ורבא אמר פסוק ראשון לחודיה. lav
davka nakat perek rishon dehaynu aliba deRava veRava amar pasuk rishon lechudei.
So תוספות Tosafot says you know there's a whole debate, first פסוק,
pasuk, first two פסוקים, psukim, first פרק. perek. But there's at the
beginning of שמע Shema requires כוונה kavannah and there you have to
stop working, stand still and focus. After that you can even continue
in working as you're saying the שמע. Shema. Okay.
Right, you know it's like that old story, I forget which Hasidic
רבי rebbe they say it about, but you know they say the
Hasidic רבי rebbe and ליטוואק Litvak are walking and they see a
guy there you know he's like he's taking off, changing the tires
on his wagon and his hands are full of grease and he's
דאווענינג, davening, you
know. So.
look at your people, even when their hands are dirty with grease,
they're still thinking about you.
So it was רבי לוי יצחק? Rebbe Levi Yitzchak? Yeah. So anyway,
so here's the עוסק במצוה, Ossek B'Mitzvah, right? You care. But anyway,
but of course it's not the first פסוק. Passuk. Okay. So,
so now we say.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. הפועלים שהיו עושים מלאכה אצל בעל הבית,
Hapoalim shehayu ossim melacha etzel baal habayit, קורין קריאת שמע korin Kriyat
Shma ומברכין לפניה ולאחריה. umvarchin lefaneha u'leachareha. פועלים Poalim that were working
by their by their employer, by the בעל הבית, Baal Habayit, homeowner,
they say the שמע Shma and they can make the ברכות Brachot
at the beginning and the end, right? Because going back to the
other question, חיים's Chaim question, I mean he had a different question
but the point is, maybe we don't even allow them to say
the ברכות Brachot of שמע? Shma? Maybe just say שמע? Shma? No,
actually we give them a certain amount of leeway. They can say
the ברכות Brachot beginning and end. ואוכלין פיתן V'ochlin pittan ומברכין לפניה
ולאחריה. umvarchin lefaneha u'leachareha. They can eat their bread and they ברכה
Bracha in the beginning and the end. For all of us like
like the quest like I think at least for me it's like
I'm shocked at the הוה אמינא. hava amina. Like you would actually
think we let somebody eat eat without making a ברכה, Bracha, without
בענטשינג? benching? And yeah, we would have thought that. You have some
maybe you have such a responsibility to your employer that you can't
even take out the minute to say המוציא לחם מן הארץ. Hamotzi
lechem min haaretz. But no, those basic things are we do allow.
Didn't mention washing. Didn't mention washing, that's true. ומתפללין תפילה של שמונה
עשרה, U'mitpallelin Tefilah Shel Shemoneh Esrei, and you can and you can
דאווען. daven. Now none of this is at the top of the
tree. This is the amount of time you're allowed to take out
to actually do these ritual requirements that we have to assume you
sort of you know we we as חז״ל Chazal can say you're
entitled and then that becomes the implicit structure of every employment agreement
that you have the right to do this. What?
This is the assumed sequence.
Oh, you mean
you say the שמע, Shma, then you eat the ברכות, Brachot, then
you have breakfast, and breakfast is not a הפסק, hefsek, then גאולה
לתפילה. geulah l'tfilah.
Oh, you mean answering חיים's Chaim point.
We've missed חיים's Chaim point questions somewhere before, not very far.
Yeah, yeah, but
why would that be?
Why would that be? Why would you interrupt with the with breakfast
and not just finish with the שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei?
I'm just reading the words.
I understand, I'm just wondering why. Before you go to work. What?
Presumably it wasn't time early enough.
No, but the point,
you would go to work like before daybreak, you
say גאל ישראל Gaal Yisrael and then he had Cheerios
and then the
זמן, zman, I
know but I know but I know but but he's asking another
question. He's saying why not דאווען daven before you go to work?
So that I assume it's just wasn't it wasn't זמן zman yet.
You were starting starting so early.
Okay, this is dark, this is dark. Right.
Be in
the tree when it's dark, when it's too early to say שמע?
Shma?
Yeah, presumably you could, I mean it's a good question how early
but look, I mean people do there are jobs that start really
4, 5 AM, right?
I assume this is allowing assuming.
Thanks,
thanks,
thanks to a bunch of sources that say that you have to
do the abridged דאווענינג. davening.
We're getting there. I don't know why I said this, הגמרא the
Gemara is about to say this. No, but דוב's Dov question is
interesting about why it interrupts this. I mean, I could create create
a specific אוקימתא ukimta that it's not yet the זמן שמונה עשרה,
zman Shemoneh Esrei, but even there we'd say you don't have to
you don't have to wait till the זמן שמונה עשרה. zman Shemoneh
Esrei. You're right, it's fascinating if we take that this order is
saying that this is really the order you do it. Why, why
I don't know, but it's an excellent point.
Okay, and when there's a conflict that that set of things have
to be done simultaneously.
Yeah, but normally we make sure that, right, that the that the
שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei comes together. Anyway, so the הגמרא the Gemara
continues: אבל אין יורדין לפני התיבה. Aval ein yordin lifnei hateivah.
You cannot go in front of the ark, meaning you can't go
to a שול shul to דאווען, daven, which is like relatively obvious,
but maybe not so much. Oh, if you can do these things
and be פרום, frum, maybe I have to take off a half
hour, I have to go דאווען daven at שול shul before I'll
come back? Okay, there are some people that think that way. ואין
נושאים כפיהם, V'ein nossim kapeihem, and you cannot do, you know, and
and you can't do ברכת כהנים. Birkat Kohanim. Now
again, like if you're not going to שול shul where you doing
ברכת כהנים? Birkat Kohanim? But maybe there are ten workers, they're all
getting together and they're דאווענינג davening together, you know. So, which brings
up interesting questions. If that was true, could you do חזרת הש״ץ
Chazarat Hashatz or maybe you're not allowed to do that?
Right? I was thinking about you as the כהן kohen or the?
You're the כהן. kohen. You're the כהן. kohen. Or maybe it's a
different thing. Maybe ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim is different than שול. shul.
You say, okay, I understand I don't go to שול shul for
תפילה בציבור, tefilah b'tzibbur, but I'm a כהן! kohen! I have to
go do ברכת כהנים! Birkat Kohanim! Okay. Yes.
But the expression in is אין יורדין לפני התיבה ein yordin lifnei
hateivah meaning as a שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, that's what רש״י Rashi
says.
Right, I said that.
But you said even to go to שול. shul.
Right. Well, cause you can't do a שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, yeah,
I assume you're right. I mean that's the question is, why doesn't
it say you can't go to שול? shul? Why does it say,
I assume it's similar to the נושאים כפיהם. nossim kapeihem. You might
think, oh, they need me, I'm the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. You
know, it's something like, oh, they need me, I'm a כהן. kohen.
Like, I have a חשוב chashuv role here, I gotta leave and
go do this. So I assume that's right.
Yeah, right. Okay. So it says, okay, דתניא, de-tanya, we talk in
a ברייתא beraita of מעין שמונה עשרה. me-ein shemoneh esrei. You can't
take a big break to say the whole שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei.
You can only say the short version of the שמונה עשרה. shemoneh
esrei. הביננו, Havineinu, right, there's a basic שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei which
is the first three ברכות, brachot, a middle paragraph that is a
summary of all of the middle stuff, and the last three ברכות.
brachot. So that's all we let you say. אמר רב ששת לא
קשיא. Amar Rav Sheshet lo kashya. That's not difficult. הא רבן גמליאל
והא רבי יהושע. Ha Rabban Gamliel ve-ha Rabbi Yehoshua. It's a debate
of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. We know
later on that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that any day if
you want to you could say the short version, the Reader's Digest
version. So he's saying it here too. So the גמרא Gemara says:
wait a minute. אי רבי יהושע, Ee Rabbi Yehoshua, if it's
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, why hear workers? אפילו כל אדם, afilu kol
adam, he lets you do the short version any person. נמי. Nami.
אלא הא והא רבן גמליאל. Ella hadei v'adei Rabban Gamliel. Obviously where
those that are allowing the abridged version is because of your responsibilities
to your employer. So fine, they're both רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So
when are you allowed to say the abridged and when not? So
it says ולא קשיא. v'lo kashya. כאן בעושים בשכרן כאן בעושים בסעודתן.
kan b'osim bis'charan, kan b'osim bisudatan. Are they doing it for their
fee
or for their meal? And רש"י Rashi says what that means is
that if you're a job that's remunerating you enough that it's pay...
some jobs you'd only get paid by being able to get your
meal. Meaning your whole pay would be that you're fed. Okay, so
that job is something that, you know, is,
that job is something that, you know, is already are, in a
way the way רש"י Rashi explains, the way I interpret רש"י, Rashi,
is that חז"ל Chazal here are coming to protect people that are
at such a low rate of, at such a low rung of
the economic scale, that if you're doing all this work and just
getting a meal out of it, we're going to allow you to
actually דאבן daven a full שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. We're going to
give you a bigger break. If you're actually getting paid well for
your job then, you know, then you have to do a short
שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Maybe also it would be cheating your employer
more, you're getting paid so well and you're taking out more time.
I did wonder if there's a possible alternative interpretation, which
is: are you given a lunch break or not? I wondered if
that was a possible read, right? That if you're given a lunch
break, עושים בסעודתן, osim bisudatan, then if you're already getting breaks, your
job includes breaks, it would also implicitly include maybe a bigger break
for דאבנינג. davening. But if you don't get a lunch break, then
the implicit assumption is you don't have any time to yourself and
you have to do the opposite in order to protect the people
who are being mistreated. Right, so that's the question: Are we trying
to go to implicitly what's the employment agreement, or is we as
חז"ל Chazal coming in as social engineers and trying to sort of
protect the disadvantaged?
Because it's the worker's rights. If it's some... if they're so poor
and that they're doing it for food. So it's I think that
might be why.
Oh, it's emphasizing the אוכלים פיתן ochlin pitan is in the first
ברייתא beraita which shows that it's the people that are basically working
for their meal. Is that your point? Yeah, the way רש"י Rashi
is. Okay, that's a good point also, picking up on the אוכלים
פיתן. ochlin pitan. So now the גמרא Gemara continues and says like
this: Where are we?
Okay, דתניא, de-tanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא: beraita: הפועלים שהיו
עושים מלאכה אצל בעל הבית קורין קריאת שמע ומתפללין ואוכלין פיתן ואין
מברכין לפניה אבל מברכין לאחריה. Ha-poalim she-hayu osim melacha l'baal ha-bayis, korein
k'riyas shema u-mitpallelin v'ochlin pitan v'ein me-varchin l'faneha aval me-varchin l'achareha. Here
we have a ברייתא beraita that says that when they come to
eat, they cannot make a ברכה bracha beforehand because the ברכה bracha
beforehand is Rabbinic. They can make the ברכה bracha after, that's Biblical,
but not the ברכה bracha beforehand. אבל מברכין לאחריה שתיים. Aval me-varchin
l'achareha shtayim. And
even the benching has to be in an abridged benching. What's the
abridged benching? כיצד? Keitzad?
ברכה ראשונה כתיקונה. Bracha rishona k'tikunah. The first ברכה bracha you say
fully. שניה פותח בברכת הארץ, Shniya poteach b'birchas ha-aretz, right, על הארץ
ועל המזון. al ha-aretz v'al ha-mazon. So the second ברכה, bracha, it's
about not just, it's about the land and not just the food
but the land.
וכולל בונה ירושלים בברכת הארץ, v'kolel b'voneh yerushalayim b'birchas ha-aretz, and you
include the theme of בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim in the second ברכה.
bracha. And the fourth ברכה bracha you forget all, you drop completely
because the fourth ברכה bracha is Rabbinic. חז"ל Chazal understood that not
only is benching Biblical, but the three themes of הזן את הכל,
hazan et hakol, על הארץ ועל המזון, al ha-aretz v'al ha-mazon, and
בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim (or one would imagine different when there was
a built Jerusalem) but anyway those three themes are Biblical themes. The
fourth one is Rabbinic. So basically you say an abridged benching and
you combine ברכות brachot two and three. So according to this version,
you only do the Biblical stuff. You don't do the Rabbinic stuff.
And we might as well also add that by the שמע, Shema,
how is it different from the previous ברייתא? beraita? This just says
you say the שמע. Shema. The previous ברייתא beraita said you say
the ברכות brachot of the שמע. Shema. So according to this, we
let you do only the bare bones, right, only the Biblical, the
שמע Shema and then an abridged benching. You drop המוציא לחם מן
הארץ, hamotzi lechem min ha-aretz, you drop the ברכות brachot of שמע,
Shema, only the Biblical stuff. So how do you reconcile these two
things?
כיצד? Keitzad? ברכה ראשונה... Bracha rishona... Oh, I just did that. במה
דברים אמורים? B'meh devarim amurim? So now it tells you. בעושים בשכרן.
B'osim b'scharan. That is when people are doing... are getting paid for
their work. Then you can take... you can only take off very
little time. And you can only do the- strict biblical requirements. אבל
עושים בסעודתן, Aval osim bisudatan, if you're working for your meal and
then we're going to give you a little more time. או שהיה
בעל הבית מיסב עמהם, O she'haya ba'al habayis meiseiv imahem, right or
the owner is eating with you, so that's basically sending you a
signal that presumably you can take a bigger break. In that case,
מברכין כתיקונה mevarchin ketikunah you can make the right ברכות. berachos. But
there, maybe the מברכין כתיקונה mevarchin ketikunah goes on the meal. If
he's eating with you, right presumably if he's eating with you there
isn't the signal that I can do the שמע Shema with the
ברכות. berachos. Presumably that's the signal that I can make the ברכות
berachos before and after. Okay, so again it raises, you know, it
raises that interesting question about how does the issue of being done
for the meal does that give me more latitude for other things?
But here we are saying that the answer is yes, that if
all you get is your meal that also gives you more latitude
to do a full שמונה עשרה. shmonah esrei. So very interesting here
we are finding, you know, when we had the משנה mishna the
only question was like, you know, like
the basic message of the משנה mishna was you've got to do
your obligation,
if you can do it at the top of the tree you
do it, if you can't do it till you get to the
bottom then you get to the bottom like the difference between שמע
Shema and שמונה עשרה. shmonah esrei. Basically tipping in favor of you've
got to make sure you fully do your obligation. In the גמרא
Gemara we see differently. We see that there are times where we
don't even let you do your full obligations, where we don't let
you say a full שמונה עשרה, shmonah esrei, maybe we don't even
let you say the ברכות berachos before and after שמע, Shema, maybe
we don't even let you say the ברכות berachos of המוציא לחם
מן הארץ Hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz under certain circumstances your responsibilities to
your employers trump not only doing not doing things a hundred percent
but even that you have to forgo some of your real obligations.
Can we infer from here that if somebody just said the first
ברכה beracha of ברכת המזון Birkas Hamazon that he's not יוצא דאורייתא?
yotzei de'oraisa?
Yes, that's the general assumption.
Okay but is that really so?
Well, okay, that's an interesting question but a lot of פוסקים poskim
do assume that that the themes of the first three ברכות berachos
are required דאורייתא. de'oraisa. We'll talk about it more when we get
to the שביעי פרק. shevi'i perek. Okay, now we get to the
end of the משנה. mishna. חתן פטור מקריאת שמע. Chassan patur mikrias
Shema. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. בשבתך בביתך Beshivtecha beviesecha when you're sitting
in your house פרט לעוסק במצוה perat le'osek be'mitzvah if you're doing
a מצוה mitzvah you're פטור patur from other מצות mitzvos and from
שמע. Shema. ובלכתך בדרך Uvlechticha baderech when you go on your way
פרט לחתן. perat le'chassan. They're exempting a groom that he doesn't have
to say שמע. Shema. מכאן אמרו הקונה את הבתולה פטור ואת האלמנה
חייב Mikan amru hakoneh es habesulah patur ve'es ha'almanah chayav that a
guy who's marrying a virgin is exempt and a widow is obligated.
Presumably the difference being that in one case he's more anxious about
the wedding night than in the other. Now maybe it would also
be an issue whether he has you know it's the first time
for him or not, but maybe part of the anxiety is not
just the act of sex but also whether she's going to be
a virgin which as we know from בתולות Besulos was a high
degree of anxiety. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara says, מאי משמע? mai
mashma? Where do you get that from the פסוק? pasuk? אמר רב
פפא Amar Rav Papa we had this exact גמרא Gemara before word
for word and actually if you look at a little רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says כבר פירשתיה בפרק ראשון. kvar peirashtia beperek rishon. Even
רש"י Rashi doesn't bother repeating this. It's word for word a גמרא
Gemara we had earlier. Okay, anyways the גמרא Gemara says where do
you get it from the פסוק? pasuk? אמר רב פפא Amar Rav
Papa כדרך kederech like a way when you go on the way
מה דרך רשות אף כל נמי רשות. mah derech reshus af kol
nami reshus. The same way when you go on your journey it's
רשות reshus it's like it's not an obligation it's you know it's
your discretion. So when you do things that are discretionary you have
to say שמע. Shema. When you do מצות mitzvos you don't have
to say שמע. Shema. The גמרא Gemara says what how do you
know? מי לא עסקינן דקאזיל לדבר מצוה? mi lo askinan dekazil lidevar
mitzvah? Maybe it's talking about that you're doing a מצוה mitzvah and
you have to say שמע? Shema? ואפילו הכי אמר רחמנא ליקרי. va'afilu
hachi amar Rachmana likri. Even so the תורה Torah says read. No,
אם כן לימא קרא ובלכת im kein leima kra uvelachet when you're
going. מאי ובלכתך mai uvlechticha your going when it's your when it's
just for you. שמע מינה בלכת דידך הוא דמיחייבת. shema mina belachet
didach hu demichayaves. That's when you say
שמע. Shema. הא דמצוה ha demitzvah פטור patur you're exempt. Okay so
if it's about doing a מצוה mitzvah says the גמרא Gemara אי
הכי מאי איריא הקונה את הבתולה? ei hachi mai irya hakoneh es
habesulah?
Why is it limited to the guy marrying the virgin? אפילו קונה
את האלמנה נמי? afilu koneh es ha'almanah nami? Even marrying a widow
you're doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay getting married is a מצוה. mitzvah.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכא טריד והכא לא טריד. hacha tarid
vehacha lo tarid. No, in both cases they're doing a מצוה mitzvah
but in the one he is distracted he is and in the
other he's not distracted he's so the question is of course so
what is the exempt of the חתן? chassan? Is the exempt that
he's עוסק במצוה osek be'mitzvah or is the exempt that he's not
able to have the right כוונה kavanah that he's distracted? So that's
the question the גמרא Gemara asks. Meaning you could say that if
I'm not distracted then I'm just sitting and waiting for the for
nighttime. I'm not עוסק במצוה. osek be'mitzvah. I'm just sitting around, I'm
waiting. Okay but if I'm distracted that somehow makes me עוסק. osek.
At least I'm עוסק osek in my mind, I'm involved in it.
But maybe the difference is just not about מצות mitzvos but about
distraction. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי משום טירדא, ei mishum tirda, if it's about distraction, so
אפילו טבעה ספינתו בים afilu tave'ah sefinaso bayam it doesn't have to
do with a מצוה mitzvah distraction. Even if your boat sank in
the sea and you're distracted for because there was other bad things
happening to your things you were worried about. נמי. nami. So אלמה
אמר רבי אבא בר זבדא אמר רב אבל חייב בכל המצות האמורות
בתורה Alama amar Rabbi Abba bar Zavda amar Rav aveil chayav bechol
hamitzvos ha'amuros baTorah חוץ מן התפילין שהרי נאמר בהם פאר. chutz min
hatefillin sheharei ne'emar bahem pe'er. Actually
this is a little bit of an abbreviated version of what we
had earlier. That I'll show you though that it's not true that
other distractions don't exempt you. We say that an אבל aveil a
mourner is obligated in all. all מצוות Mitzvot except for תפילין Tefillin
on the first day because they're glory and that's inappropriate for the
first day, but a mourner clearly is distracted about thoughts of his
grief and even so he says the שמע. Shema. So you see
normal distraction doesn't exempt you. So the
גמרא Gemara says: התם טירדא דרשות הכא, Hatam tirda di'reshut hacha, excuse
me,
פאר חבוש עליך, Pe'er chavosh alecha, the prophet יחזקאל, Yechezkel, remove your
glory which we understand means remove the תפילין Tefillin because you're an
אבל. Avel. אמרי, Amri, so there's a difference. התם טירדא דרשות הכא
טירדא דמצוה. Hatam tirda di'reshut hacha tirda di'mitzvah. There's a distraction which
is sort of discretionary. Nobody's telling you it's now, you could say
by the אבל, Avel, you know, that's part of sitting שבעה, Shiva,
you wouldn't necessarily call it טירדא דרשות, Tirda di'reshut, but nevertheless it's
not somehow it's not about being planning and thinking about a מצוה
Mitzvah you're going to be doing, so we wouldn't call it עוסק
במצוה. Osek bi'mitzvah. Whereas here, you know, because it's about being preoccupied
with thoughts of an act you're going to be doing, now you're
not necessarily so פרום Frum that you're worried about am I going
to be יוצא Yotzei the מצוה, Mitzvah, but you are worried about
something you're going to be doing that is a מצוה. Mitzvah. That's
considered somehow to be a mental עוסק במצוה, Osek bi'mitzvah, which is
less than in these two cases. I have to tell you at
the end of the day, it's hard for me to understand why
the חתן Chassan case is more עוסק במצוה Osek bi'mitzvah than the
אבל Avel case. Number one, unless part of the message is that
part of אבלות Avelus is to sort of work through the issues
and not be sort of overly indulged in that. I don't know.
But number two is, what with רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel? Right, תוספות
Tosfot says basically רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says: I'm able to have
כוונה Kavana even on the wedding night. Okay, but according to the
גמרא Gemara it wasn't about whether you're able to have כוונה, Kavana,
according to the גמרא Gemara it was that you're עוסק במצוה. Osek
bi'mitzvah. So in the end of the day it sounds like the
חתן Chassan has a lot to do with the issue of focus
and distraction and not the technical exemption of עוסק במצוה, Osek bi'mitzvah,
and the גמרא Gemara itself is sort of working, you know, trying
to work that through.
What you're saying to me, from what you're explaining, is that on
a continuum, כוונה Kavana and the ability to focus, the sense of
interiority is at one end. Right. אבלות Avelus is the paradigm on
the opposite end. Right.
And אבלות, Avelus, but it's saying that you're not exempt, but it's
saying you're not exempt by אבלות, Avelus, you have to say the
שמע. Shema.
That's the problem. That by the אבל Avel we're saying he has
to say the שמע, Shema, but the חתן Chassan doesn't.
But it's still set up that way, that's problematic.
Right, right, exactly, exactly.
The opposite of the ability to have כוונה Kavana is אבלות.
Avelus. Right. So this גמרא Gemara seems to be saying, this גמרא
Gemara seems to be saying
it's not about כוונה, Kavana, it's about עוסק במצוה. Osek bi'mitzvah. If
it's about עוסק במצוה, Osek bi'mitzvah, what's with רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel?
If it's about כוונה, Kavana, you can say oh, I'm able to
focus and have כוונה. Kavana.
Well, when we set that up, you're fine, I'm saying you can
be done with the act on the wedding night and your grief
doesn't have an end.
Aha. So therefore we want, so therefore we don't want to sort
of validate that עוסק Osek in that sense.
We want, right,
as soon as you're done with this, then you can start resuming
the שמע. Shema. But it's not really a concept that as soon
as you're done with...
I see your point. So even if you're supposed to be thinking
about it now in a way we don't want to validate that
involvement because the whole idea is to be working through it and
to be done with it. Right.
And furthermore on the second day you begin to immediately reproduce a
structure in your brain.
Right. And in a way that is the difference between אנינות Aninus
and אבלות. Avelus. That אנינות Aninus is you're so absorbed within it
that we're not asking you to sort of get out of it,
and אבלות Avelus is the beginning of moving out of it. And
I mean, that's a nice way of saying it. So the whole
difference of אנינות Aninus and אבלות Avelus is we're moving you out
of that complete absorption and therefore we don't want to further sort
of, you know, entrench it.
Maybe to their credit they didn't want to make sex on your
wedding night and mourning the same thing.
Well, that's true, but those wouldn't necessarily have only been comparisons, but
yes.
So getting back to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, when we say פטור,
Patur, does that mean he's not allowed, or it's okay if he
doesn't?
Well, apparently his sons thought that he wasn't allowed. That it's, you
know, and he said, I mean, it's, you know, that
that was his interpretation.
I understand what you're asking. But if it was עוסק במצוה Osek
bi'mitzvah we would say you're not allowed to do another מצוה. Mitzvah.
If it's עוסק במצוה, Osek bi'mitzvah, normal עוסק במצוה Osek bi'mitzvah you're
not allowed to leave the מצוה Mitzvah and do another מצוה. Mitzvah.
Okay, so let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So there is this
question about is this שמע Shema thing about עוסק במצוה Osek bi'mitzvah
or about כוונה. Kavana. Anyway, now that we're on רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel we have a couple of more interesting stories about him. רחץ
לילה הראשון שמת אשתו. Rachatz layla harishon shemes ishto. Talking about אבלות,
Avelus, so he bathed, washed himself the first night after his wife
had died and apparently been buried that day. אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru
lo talmidav, so his students said to him: למדתנו רבנו שאבל אסור
לרחוץ, Lamedtanu rabbeinu she'avel asur lirkotz, you've taught us that a mourner
should not bathe. So אמר להם Amar lahem he said to them:
איני כשאר בני אדם אסטניס אני, Eini kisher bnei adam istnis ani,
so here I'm not פרומר Frummer than other people, here I'm more,
you know, I'm more finicky, that's a better word than finicky, fastidious,
and therefore I cannot go a day without bathing. תוספות Tosfot points
out that it's not a special allowance we give him, oh אסטניס
Istnis has an exemption. It's that the nature of the washing and
bathing that's forbidden is bathing of pleasure. And when you're doing it
because you need to for basic cleanliness and it's sort of painful
for you not to be. to bathe and it's not for pleasure
and therefore it's acceptable. Okay, check that as well. Oh by the
way, it's very relevant also like the nine days when it's hot
and sweaty or whatever, that דין din about bathing for pleasure. You
need to take a shower to clean off, you can. וכשמת טבי
עבדו, U'keshe'meis Tabi avdo, now when Tabi his servant died, a lot
of famous stories about Tabi, who was a very like they actually
had a lot of halakhic discussions with Tabi involved and like things
that he was doing. Anyway, קיבל עליו תנחומים, kibel alav tanchumim, he
accepted consolers for when for the death of his servant. He didn't
have a מצוה mitzvah of sitting שבעה, shiva, but he accepted people
to come and to wish him consolation after his servant died. Tabi
died. אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru lo talmidav, his students said to him:
לא למדתנו רבנו שאין מקבלין תנחומים על העבדים, lo limadetanu rabeinu she'ein
mekabelin tanchumim al ha'avadim, haven't you taught us that you do not
accept consolers for the death of slaves? אמר להם, Amar lahem, אין
טבי עבדי כשאר כל העבדים, כשר היה. ein Tabi avdi k'sha'ar kol
ha'avadim, kasher hayah. He is not like other slaves. He was a
real good person. He was a real like, you know, sort of
kosher person. Now this seems to suggest that the reason that you
don't accept consolers for slaves, I mean it's an interesting question, right,
about slaves become like members of the household and you start, you
know, they're like part of the family. Why don't you? So could
we read this משנה mishnah to say, oh, because חז"ל Chazal thought
that all slaves are terrible people and therefore whatever? I don't think
so, I think there is a concern about maintaining certain boundaries, right,
and about as the גמרא Gemara says later, question about like יוחסין.
yuchsin. If you start really treating them as members of the household
then people, then they'll be confused with free people and people and
and that question about who marriage and a lot of other issues.
So it's some issue of, right, yes they become like family members
but at certain point you have to draw boundaries. Of course if
that was true you would understand why Tabi is different, you still
have to draw a certain boundary. But he was prepared to make
an exception. Tabi was such a good person, you know, that for
him I'm willing to do it. I'm willing to break that to
break that line.
I know, that's the message.
It sounds wrong.
That's the message.
The message is, well you could say that, you could say he
operates out of the rules, but you could also say it's a
difference between ראש קטן rosh katan and ראש גדול. rosh gadol. Like
his students, his main students, they're always like, oh but what about,
you know, but this is this, you know, all they can think
about is, you know, applying the הלכה, halakhah, the same הלכה halakhah
to every single case. And they're not willing to understand that there
actually is more give within the halakhic system and sometimes cases have
to be evaluated differently. So yes, you could read it he's making
his own rules, but you could also read it that his students
are wait, wait, this is the rule, this is the rule and
they're not able to see that I'm above all that.
I can read שמע Shema on the night I'm married. I can
wash the day my wife died.
Right, right.
And he's setting up a
model in which rules are contextualized.
Exactly. He's setting up the model, he's saying, right, for me. Right.
You could read it either way. You could read it either way,
yes. You could read it I make my own rules, or you
could read it, you know, when it comes to rules and הלכה,
halakhah, we have to, we have to, you know, see sometimes sometimes
the particulars of the case matter. Okay.
What?
He was a חסיד. chasid.
Right, and why he might think that he should make an exception
for himself.
Right, and that's even more interesting
because then his students will watch him and do like he says,
or
setting examples for other people that there's latitude within the law. Okay,
it's an interesting way about reading it both ways. Okay. I mean,
you know, okay, okay. Since I told you one joke I'll tell
you another one. My grandmother, עליה השלום, aleha hashalom, used to love
the story that the villagers come to the rabbi and they say,
rabbi, rabbi, the cow fell in the well! He says, you can't
do anything, it's שבת. Shabbos. But rabbi, it's your cow! צער בעלי
חיים! tza'ar ba'alei chayim! Help him! So okay, there is latitude but
we'd rather see it when you apply it to other people rather
than yourself. Okay, so anyway, all right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, okay. חתן אם רוצה לקרות קריאת שמע לילה ראשונה קורא.
Chassan im rotzeh likros krias shema lailah rishonah korei. Now it's very
interesting, because now, ah, you see Rivka, your point, in a way
the משנה mishnah is addressing because what the משנה mishnah does is
we're going to take what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel did and we're
going to say that that becomes part of the latitude within the
law. So therefore if another groom wants to read שמע Shema on
the first night he's allowed to, right, so we're going to bring
that into the law for everybody. But then look at what his
son says: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer.
So רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel son says: לא כל הרוצה ליטול את
השם יטול. lo kol ha'rotzeh litol es hashem yitol. Not everybody can
be as frum as my father. Not everybody who thinks that they're
prepared to like take God's name even when they are a חתן
chassan is prepared to do it. That was a special rule for
my father. So here exactly what we're debating
is the legacy of רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel actions. Is the legacy
that very special people like my father, or is the legacy that
there is certain latitude within the law? Okay, let's just read a
few more minutes, got to get a little further because I really
thought we were caught up, so we'll give it a few more
minutes. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama for רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, what's the
reason of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that he bathed on the first
night? קסבר אנינות לילה דרבנן, kasvar aninus lailah d'rabanan, אנינות aninus of
the first night is rabbinic. דכתיב ואחריתה כיום מר, dichsiv ve'acharisah k'yom
mar,
that afterwards of death is like a bitter day. Only the day
biblically has status of death. not the following night, ובמקום אסטניס Uve-makom
istanis לא גזרו בה רבנן lo gazru beh rabbanan and in a
place of somebody that's particularly fastidious, the Rabbis waived their demand. Now,
first of all, what are you talking about אנינות? aninus? It's אבילות.
aveilus. And an אונן, onen, right, which is the status of somebody
after the death of a relative before burial, it's very questionable if
an אונן onen is forbidden in bathing. The פשוט pashut is we
might rule that he is, but anyway, it's very basically it's very
questionable. Only the אבילות aveilus is forbidden in bathing. But the גמרא
Gemara says that the idea of אבילות aveilus that of our practice
of אבילות aveilus is learned out from the biblical concept of אנינות.
aninus. The biblical concept of אנינות, aninus, right, is very clear, ולא
אכלתי באוני ממנו, v-lo achalti v-oni mimenu, that an אונן, onen, somebody
who immediately suffered death, cannot engage in certain acts of קרבנות korbanos
and קדשים kodshim and so on. And from there, we say that
serves as a model of the status right after death, from which
we build the idea of אבילות. aveilus. Okay, but אבילות aveilus is
very distinct from אנינות, aninus, אבילות aveilus is after burial. And the
question in the גמרא Gemara and in the ראשונים Rishonim becomes, is
there any אבילות aveilus which is biblical? It may be only the
אבילות aveilus of the day of burial itself, afterwards it's all רבנן.
rabanan. And here the question is maybe the following night. So the
גמרא's Gemara answer is no, the following night he felt was רבנן
rabanan for אבילות aveilus and therefore it could be waived for him
as an אסטניס. istanis. Again, this גמרא Gemara is not תוספות. Tosafos.
תוספות Tosafos says it's because it's not the problematic bathing, it's only
bathing of pleasure, this wasn't pleasure bathing. The גמרא Gemara doesn't sound
like that. It sounds like it really is a problematic act, but
because of your special circumstances we'll forgo it.
You know that אסטניס istanis of the first three days of שבעה
shiva is אבילות. aveilus.
I remember that, but
the first three days have a different status.
But the dominant position of the דאורייתא d-Oraisa is either the first
day and some say nothing. Okay, alright, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, וכשמת טבי, V-che-she-meis Tevi, let's just get a little
further, when טבי Tevi died. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, עבדים ושפחות אין
עומדין עליהם בשורה ואין אומרים עליהם ברכת אבלים. avadim u-shfachos ein omdin
aleihem be-shura v-ein omrim aleihem birchas avelim.
So slaves and women slaves, you don't do the שורה, shura, after
burial you know there's a line of consolers that the mourners walk
between, you don't do that, and you don't give... ואין אומרים עליהם
ברכת אבלים, v-ein omrim aleihem birchas avelim, there's a ברכה bracha that
they used to have that they gave for the mourners, you don't
do that, that the consolers gave to the mourners, ותנחומי אבלים, v-tanchumei
avelim,
and you don't do the mourning for the אבלים. avelim. מעשה ומתה
שפחתו של רבי אליעזר, Maaseh u-meisah shifchaso shel Rabbi Eliezer,
so the maidservant of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer died. נכנסו תלמידיו לנחמו,
Nichnesu talmidav l-nachamo, they saw he was, you know, they saw he
was mourning emotionally even if not הלכתית, halachically, so they wanted to
give him consolation. כיון שראה אותם, Keivan she-raah osam, he saw them
coming into his house and he knew what was up, עלה לעליה,
alah l-aliyah, he quickly ran away to the second story. ונכנסו אחריו,
V-nichnesu achrav, they went after him. נכנס לאנפילון, Nichnas l-anpilon, he went
to anpilon which is some type of an antechamber. ונכנסו אחריו, V-nichnesu
achrav, they ran after him. נכנס לטרקלין, Nichnas l-traklin, he went to
the big sort of the big chamber, might also be like a
banquet hall. ונכנסו אחריו, V-nichnesu achrav, they ran after him. אמר להם,
Amar lahem, he said to them: כמדומה אני שאתם נכוים בפושרין, Kimdumeh
ani she-atem nichvim be-foshrim, I thought you were a little sharper than
that. You know, I thought that even if the water was lukewarm,
you would feel the heat, meaning you don't need things to be
obvious to you. עכשיו אי אתם נכוים אפילו בחמי חמין, Achshav ei
atem nichvim afilu be-chamei chamim, now I see that even if the
water is boiling hot, you don't feel it. You know, how much
more obvious can I get? לא כך שניתי לכם, Lo kach shanisi
lachem,
haven't I taught you? עבדים ושפחות אין עומדין עליהם בשורה ואין אומרים
עליהם ברכת אבלים, Avadim u-shfachos ein omdin aleihem be-shura v-ein omrim aleihem
birchas avelim,
you don't do any of this stuff for slaves. אלא מה אומרים
עליהם, Ela mah omrim aleihem, so what would you say for somebody
that you want to make them feel better after a slave had
died? כשם שאומרים לו לאדם על שורו ועל חמורו שמתו, Ke-shem she-omrim
lo l-adam al shoro v-al chamoro she-meisu,
like you would say if somebody's donkey died or cow died, ox
died, המקום ימלא לך חסרונך, Ha-Makom yemalei lecha chesroncha, like God fulfill
your loss, you know, but it's not the whole עסק esek of
תנחומים, tanchumim, so really very harsh, treating him completely like property. You
know, here's this whole tension of slaves as people and slaves as
property, which plays out interestingly in a number of הלכתי halachic areas.
There's no question that slaves had a הלכתי halachic status of property
in many, many ways. Okay, non-Jewish slaves. But there were elements in
which they would have had a personhood status. And here it's much
more at the sort of, you know, somewhat הלכתי, halachic, somewhat emotional
level. How do you respond to this? Like as a loss of
property or as a real sort of loss of a family member?
Now, there's a middle ground, that it could be, treat them as
humans but they're not your family, you know, so therefore you're not,
you know, so anyway, but this is, so this is going much
harsher than we had before, you know, not just saying they're not
my family but they're just property.
So the formula המקום ימלא לך חסרונך Ha-Makom yemalei lecha chesroncha is
ambiguous.
Yeah, right, I thought about that too. המקום ימלא לך חסרונך Ha-Makom
yemalei lecha chesroncha is, there's a certain ambiguous nature, but it also
suggests that something is substitutable, right. You know, one slave, another slave,
and so on.
So right, you know, it's anachronistically ironic. In other words, it's a
literal translation of "I am sorry for
your loss" and what
that suggests is that that ultimately conveys a somewhat vacuous...
No, but it would be vacuous if you said God should replace
your loss. Imagine saying that to a mourner, right? That's absurd, right?
That's heartless. So המקום ינחם אתכם. Hamakom yenachem etchem.
Okay, so it is just this
notion of language,
of right, right.
You can look at it another way, this sets precedent for mourning
rituals for pets.
Oh, that's interesting.
It's not like you bought her for.
Oh, that's an interesting point.
Of a loss of an animal, of something that you have an
emotional connection to, right. Okay, so let's just finish—that's very—let's just finish
the two dots. תניא אידך. Tanya idach. Okay, we talked about the
ברייתא. Braisa. עבדים ושפחות אין מספידין אותן. Avadim ushifachot ein maspidin otan.
רבי יוסי אומר אם עבד כשר הוא, Rabbi Yose omer im eved
kasher hu, אומרים עליו הוי איש טוב ונאמן ונהנה מיגיעו. Omrim alav
hoy ish tov vene'eman venehene miyegio.
So he says, so here we say you don't eulogize them, not
just, so it is maybe even worse. It's not just saying they're
not a family member, so you don't give this person consoling, but
you don't eulogize them and speak about them as people, as what
they achieved. So he says no you actually can. You could say
woe to this good man and he was trustworthy and he actually
worked hard and achieved the fruits of his labor. So אמרו לו
Amru lo they said back to him, אם כן מה הנחת לכשרים.
Im ken ma hanachat lekesherim. That's a pretty good eulogy! So what's
the distinction between that and what you'll say to somebody else? But
again the question of הספד hesped I think also takes it, it's
not just a question of who is the family, but it's a
question about how you relate to this loss of service. I will
end by saying it's fascinating that after the רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
story, here the students of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wanted to act
extra legally. And right they wanted to respond to his loss and
give him תנחומים. tanchumim. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was holding to
the letter of the law and he was saying no, no, no,
what are you doing? That's not the הלכה. halacha. Okay, so we
will continue with this discussion tomorrow.